Guide to the Coalition to Stop Trident Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Coalition to Stop Trident records
1960-2009
MS 1696
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
10.52
The records consist of administrative records, correspondence, publications, subject files, and photographs documenting the history, structure, philosophies, and activities of the Coalition to Stop Trident as well as other groups working to stop the production and deployment of Trident submarines and missiles in Connecticut and New England. There are also subject files which place the local activities of these Connecticut groups into the context of the national and international disarmament movement.
Coalition to Stop Trident
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Marjorie Van Cleef, 1995, 2005, 2015; Stephen Kobasa, 1998-1999, 2001-2002, 2007 and 2010; Art Laffin, 2000; and Sam Marshall, 2000.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series and eleven additions: I. Organizational Records, 1973-1993. II. Subject Files, 1969-1993. III. Visual Materials, 1981, no date.
Scope and Contents
The records of the Coalition to Stop Trident are arranged in three series and primarily document the activities of several anti-nuclear groups in Connecticut protesting against the development of the Trident military defense system. The manuscript group also holds a number of collected materials which serve to place the activities of these groups into the context of the broader national and international disarmament movements in which they took part. The administrative records of the Coalition to Stop Trident and of its predecessor, the Trident/Conversion campaign, are particularly interesting because they give an excellent example of the processes, discussions, theories, and principles common to the organization of grassroots movements. The numerous files on the demonstrations held to protest nuclear arms generally and the Trident system specifically contain substantive information which can be used to reconstruct the history of the disarmament movement in Connecticut and Southern New England. There is also ample documentation of the philosophy behind the peace and disarmament movements.
Biographical / Historical
Although the Coalition to Stop Trident (CST) was not formally established until 1984, resistance to the construction of the Trident submarines in Connecticut began with a protest during the keel laying of the first Trident, the USS Ohio, in 1976. Southeastern Connecticut became a national locus for demonstrations supporting nuclear disarmament and protesting against the construction of the Trident and other "fast attack submarines," largely because the submarines were built at Electric Boat, a ship yard situated in Groton, Connecticut. Ceremonies at Electric Boat and at nearby naval bases marking the launching and commissioning of the submarines provided high profile opportunities for protest against their construction and more broadly against the nuclear arms race.
The history of resistance to the Trident program is complex. As their name suggests, the Coalition to Stop Trident was comprised of several different local affinity groups working toward eradicating nuclear weaponry. Other groups, though not formally part of the CST, participated in and assisted with several demonstrations and actions. To further complicate matters, the work of several different groups preceded the CST in organizing resistance to Trident and other nuclear weaponry. Although perhaps slightly divided on questions of theory and method, all of these groups were united by the need to stop the production of nuclear arms, particularly in Connecticut.
"Trident" is an overall military nuclear program comprised of Trident submarines and two generations of missiles, the Trident I, which became operational in 1979 with the launching of the USS Ohio, and the Trident II, which became operational in 1986 with the launching of the USS Tennessee, the ninth Trident submarine. Planning for the Trident program began in the early 1970s. The USS Ohio was launched in 1979 and was commissioned into the United States Navy in 1981. The USS Wyoming, the seventeenth Trident, was commissioned in 1996, and the submarines continue to be produced. The Trident submarines, which measure 560 feet in length and can carry up to twenty-four highly explosive nuclear missiles with long range capabilities, brought unprecedented speed, accuracy, and power to an already potent fleet of "fast attack" submarines. Trident allowed the Navy to possess the "first strike" option, an ability to quickly attack and destroy an opponent's defenses, thereby rendering them unable to retaliate.
Anti-nuclear groups, many of which grew out of the peace movements of the late 1960s and early 1970s, saw the development of Trident as making nuclear war more dangerous and more likely. They believed that rather than acting merely as a deterrent, the faster, more accurate, and more powerful weapons would make the option of using them without retaliation more viable. The enhanced defense abilities also would cause opponents to be more likely to launch their own weapons on only the suspicion rather than the reality of an attack. Furthermore, most of these groups protested against the large budgetary allotments made to the Trident program (each submarine costs approximately two billion dollars to produce). The anti-nuclear protestors favored a conversion of the Connecticut economy from the highly influential defense industries to services which would combat the social problems of homelessness, poverty, unemployment, poor health care, and ineffective public education.
Protests against the Trident program involved many different groups and individuals. The most prominent organizations which preceded the formation of the CST included the Atlantic Life Network, the Trident/Conversion Campaign, the American Friends Service Committee of Connecticut, Connecticut Freeze Campaign, the War Resister's League, and Spinsters Opposed to Nuclear Genocide. Membership in the groups often overlapped.
The protests themselves were organized in an ad hoc manner and varied widely. The largest demonstrations usually coincided with the launching or commissioning of a new Trident submarine. Actions at these events often took on two forms: legal demonstrations and civil disobedience. Legal demonstrations included prayer vigils, leafleting, marching, "die-in's," chanting, music, street theater, and speakers. Civil disobedience technique generally consisted of attempts to disrupt the normal course of business, or celebratory activities at the site of the protest. Protestors involved in the civil disobedience actions practiced non-violence, and these actions usually resulted in their arrest.
In July 1982, a more radical form of direct action against the Trident program ensued in Connecticut when nine women and men broke into the Electric Boat shipyard, spray-painted "USS AUSCHWITZ," poured their own blood, and hammered on sonar devices on the USS Florida, the third of the Trident submarines. These nine protestors, who became known as "Trident Nein," were arrested and some of them ended up imprisoned. Protests such as these became known as "Plowshares" actions, the name being taken from the biblical verse, "and they shall beat their swords into plowshares." Plowshares actions recurred four other times in Connecticut and at Quonset Point, Rhode Island, the site of another Electric Boat shipyard. The break-ins and the trials of the Plowshares groups, especially Trident Nein and Plowshares #4, were covered extensively by local media and even received national attention. The trials and sentencings of these groups also resulted in staged demonstrations supporting their actions and protesting their incarceration.
During the weekend of June 18-20, 1983, large demonstrations were organized to protest the commissioning of the USS Florida, the third Trident submarine christened into the United States Navy, and to observe the International Day of Disarmament. Several groups and individuals formed the "June 18-20 Coalition" to plan these events. This group served as the precursor to the Coalition to Stop Trident, which formed in the early months of 1984.
The CST was initially comprised of Rhode Island Mobilization for Survival, Spinsters Opposed to Nuclear Genocide, Trident Nein, and the War Resistor's League of Norwich, Connecticut. By 1988 the CST had evolved to include the Isaiah Peace Ministry, Witness for Disarmament, New Haven Against Trident II, and Hartford Against Trident II. The CST organized and sponsored several activities ranging from educational outreach to continuing demonstrations protesting the launchings and commissionings of Trident submarines. In perhaps its most sustained effort, the CST kicked off a two-year campaign in 1986 to increase awareness about the Trident program with the goal of stopping the deployment of the Trident II missiles which became operational in December 1986. The largest of the events organized under the two-year campaign occurred on the weekend of October 24-26, 1987, dates of the twenty-fifth anniversary of the Cuban Missile Crisis and International Disarmament Day.
With the end of Cold War in the late 1980s, the intensity of the protests against the Trident program dropped off considerably. Although Trident submarines and missiles continued to be produced and deployed, the CST stopped holding regular meetings. Some of the local affinity groups which comprised the CST remained active, and new groups, such as the Trident Information Network, were formed. Through the activities of these groups, sporadic protests against Trident continued, but without reaching the same fervor as previous campaigns.
The records of the Coalition to Stop Trident are arranged in three series and primarily document the activities of several anti-nuclear groups in Connecticut protesting against the development of the Trident military defense system. The Manuscript group also holds a number of collected materials which serve to place the activities of these groups into the context of the broader national and international disarmament movements in which they took part. The administrative records of the Coalition to Stop Trident and of its predecessor, the Trident/Conversion campaign, are particularly interesting because they give an excellent example of the processes, discussions, theories, and principles common to the organization of grassroots movements. The numerous files on the demonstrations held to protest nuclear arms generally and the Trident system specifically contain substantive information which can be used to reconstruct the history of the disarmament movement in Connecticut and Southern New England. There is also ample documentation of the philosophy behind the peace and disarmament movements.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Antinuclear movement -- United States; Demonstrations; Disarmament; Economic conversion; Nuclear disarmament; Nuclear submarines; Peace movements -- Connecticut; Peace movements -- United States; Trident (Weapons systems); Photographs; Daniels, Marta; Laffin, Arthur J.; Sheehan, Joanne; American Friends Service Committee. Disarmament Program; Coalition to Stop Trident; Electric Boat Company; Plowshares Eight (Group); Plowshares Four (Group); Trident Nein; Trident/Conversion Campaign; War Resisters League
- Organizational Records, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The Organizational Records series is comprised of materials relating to resistance to the production of Trident submarines and missiles in Connecticut and New England. The series holds the most substantive records in this Manuscript group and is divided into five sections: Coalition to Stop Trident(CST) Office Files, Trident/Conversion Campaign, Other groups, Demonstrations, and Trident system files.
  Arranged alphabetically, the Coalition to Stop Trident Office Files contain administrative records and organizing materials used by the Coalition. Brief histories of the CST can be found in "Brochures and newsletters, 1985, 1988" and "Grant applications 1986-1988." "Minutes and agendas, 1984-1988" hold valuable information on the history, structure, methods, and philosophies of the CST. Information on the orientation of the group is supplemented by materials found in "Goals and objectives, 1985-1986." Though far from complete, "Staff reports, 1988" provides a view of the activities of paid staff members of the CST. Other materials, including those found in "Organizing resources, n.d.," "Civil disobedience handbooks, 1983-1988, n.d.," and "Non-violence training materials, 1984, n.d.," were used by the CST when organizing their activities.
  The Trident/Conversion Campaign (T/CC) section holds materials relating to this predecessor of the CST, which was formed in 1978. Much of the work done by the T/CC was performed through the American Friends Service Committee of Connecticut (AFSC) whose staff members were Marta Daniels and Bruce Martin. Most of the "Correspondence, 1977-1983" was generated or received by Daniels and Martin and was written on AFSC stationery. These letters contain valuable information on many topics relating to anti-Trident work in Connecticut and elsewhere. Daniels was also a prolific writer on anti-nuclear issues, and a sampling of her work is found in "Daniels, Marta-Writings, 1977-1981, n.d." Finally, "Minutes, 1978-1989," and "Goals and strategies, 1979" provide information on the beginning of the T/CC and of its principles and activities.
  Other Connecticut Groups is a small but significant section which documents the work of organizations distinct from the CST and the T/CC but which did related work against Trident in Connecticut. "Atlantic Life Community, 1983-1985" holds several leaflets distributed to workers each week in a campaign at the Electric Boat shipyard. "Connecticut Freeze Campaign, 1981-1990" contains several different types of materials, including press releases, news clippings, flyers, and correspondence which document the activities of this group. "Ministry with Defense Workers, 1983-1984" is comprised of the correspondence, newsletters, and organizing resources of a group of local clergy who worked with employees of Electric Boat who were distraught about building nuclear weapons for a living. Finally, "Trident Information Network, 1992-1993" holds newsletters from a group which was a successor to the CST.
  The multiple actions taken by groups against the production of Trident are well documented in the Demonstrations section. This section is divided into three sub-sections, Trident Demonstrations, Other Demonstrations, and Plowshares, each of which is organized chronologically. The Trident actions pertain to protests of launchings (the first time a submarine goes out to sea), sea trials, or commissionings (when the submarine is christened into the fleet of the United States Navy) of new Trident submarines at Electric Boat shipyard in Groton or a nearby naval base in New London. Clippings from news coverage by local papers comprise the bulk of these records, but flyers, mailings, and leaflets are also included. Folders in Other Demonstrations contain similar materials about actions organized to protest nuclear weapons other than Trident. These demonstrations often coincided with the launching or commissioning of "fast attack submarines," and religious holidays. Performed by small, independent groups, Plowshares actions were direct attempts to sabotage the production of nuclear weaponry. These folders contain several clippings about the actions themselves and the trials of the individuals involved. These actions also spawned groups to support the Plowshares groups financially and morally as they faced incarceration. "Support groups" contain newsletters and mailings about the status of the trials faced by the members of the different Plowshares groups.
  The Trident System Files, the bulk of which are news clippings, document the production of the Trident submarines and missiles by their sole contractor, the Electric Boat division of General Dynamics. The "Alternative Use Study, 1984-1985" explores the possibility of a conversion of Electric Boat from the production of nuclear weapons to non-military commodities. Relations between Electric Boat and its employees are documented in "Employee lay-offs, 1977-1978," "Employee strike, 1988," and "Proescher, Richard, 1978-1980." The most substantive documentation on Trident submarines is held in "DMS Profiles, n.d.," "Fact sheets, n.d.," and "Technical Explanations, 1982-1986, n.d.." Finally, "Position papers, 1977-1983" contains articles both for and against the Trident system.
  - Coalition to Stop Trident office files
    - Articles and clippings, 1983-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bibliographies and publications lists, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Brochures and newsletters, 1985, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Civil disobedience handbooks, 1983-1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Fund raising, 1986, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Goals and objectives, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Grant applications, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Graphics samples, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Leaflets and flyers, 1987-1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Letters of support, 1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Mailings, 1984-1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Minutes [minutes of the June 18-20 Coalition], 1983 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Minutes and agendas, 1984-1988 (Box 1, Folder 14-16)
    - New England Grassroots Peace Directory, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Non-violence training materials, 1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Organizing resources, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Press releases, 1984-1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Staff reports, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Stickers and buttons, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Two year campaign, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Trident/Conversion Campaign
    - General, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Brochures, 1976-1978, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence [mostly incoming/outgoing of Marta Daniels and Bruce Martin], 1977-1983 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Daniels, Marta
      - Biographical information, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Writings, 1977-1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Goals and strategies, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Information packet, 1973-1979 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Legislative task force, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Minutes, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - "Peace Conversion: A Case Study" [paper by Peter DeBiasi on the Trident/Conversion Campaign], 1979 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Other Connecticut groups
    - Atlantic Life Community [leaflet campaign at Electric Boat Shipyard], 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Connecticut Freeze Campaign [Connecticut Campaign for a US-USSR Nuclear Arms Freeze], 1981-1990 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Ministry with Defense Workers, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Trident Information Network, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Demonstrations, 1977-1993
    - Trident
      - 1979
        - USS Ohio launching, Apr 7 (Box 3, Folder 38-39)
      - 1980
        - USS Michigan launching, Apr 26 (Box 3, Folder 40)
      - 1981
        - USS Ohio sea trials, Jun 17 (Box 3, Folder 41)
        - USS Ohio commissioning, Nov 11
          - Clippings (Box 3, Folder 42)
          - Organizing materials (Box 3, Folder 43)
        - USS Florida launching, Nov 14 (Box 3, Folder 44)
      - 1982
        - USS Michigan commissioning, Sep 11 (Box 3, Folder 45)
        - USS Georgia launching, Nov 6 3 (Box 3, Folder 46)
      - 1983
        - USS Florida commissioning, Jun 18
          - Clippings (Box 3, Folder 47)
          - Organizing materials (Box 3, Folder 48)
        - USS Jackson launching, Oct 15 (Box 3, Folder 49)
      - 1984
        - USS Alabama launching, May 19 (Box 3, Folder 50)
        - USS Jackson commissioning, Oct 7 (Box 3, Folder 51)
      - 1985
        - USS Nevada launching, Sep 14 (Box 3, Folder 52)
      - 1986
        - USS Alaska commissioning, Jan 25 (Box 4, Folder 53)
        - USS Nevada commissioning, Aug 16 (Box 4, Folder 54)
        - USS Tennessee launching, Dec 13 (Box 4, Folder 55)
      - 1988
        - USS Pennsylvania launching, Apr 23 (Box 4, Folder 56)
      - 1989
        - USS Pennsylvania commissioning, Sep 9 (Box 4, Folder 57)
        - USS West Virginia launching, Oct 14 (Box 4, Folder 58)
      - 1992
        - USS Nebraska launching, Aug 15 (Box 4, Folder 59)
      - 1993
        - USS Rhode Island launching, Jul 17 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Other
    - 1977
      - "Stop the Trident," May 21 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - 1980
      - USS Baltimore [fast attack submarine launching], Dec 13 (Box 4, Folder 62)
      - Lenten peace vigils, Mar-Apr (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - 1981
      - "Days of October" [Franciscan vigil of peace] (Box 4, Folder 64)
      - "Affirmation of Life Gathering," Oct 31 (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - 1983
      - Feminists Against Trident, Jan 1 (Box 4, Folder 66)
      - USS Corpus Christi [fast attack submarine launching], Jan 8 (Box 4, Folder 67)
      - USS Minneapolis/St. Paul [fast attack submarine launching], Mar 19 (Box 4, Folder 68)
      - Good Friday, Apr 1 (Box 4, Folder 69)
      - "MayDay! MayDay!," May 1 (Box 4, Folder 70)
      - USS Rickover [fast attack submarine launching], Aug 2 (Box 4, Folder 71)
      - Women of Faith, Oct 3 (Box 4, Folder 72)
      - "Santa Claus Action," Dec 22 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - 1984
      - Anniversary of the bombing of Hiroshima and Nagasaki, Aug 6, 9 (Box 4, Folder 74)
      - "Harvest of Life," Oct 27 (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - 1985
      - Women of Faith [Norwich, Connecticut], Feb (Box 4, Folder 76)
      - Good Friday, Apr 5 (Box 4, Folder 77)
      - North Atlantic Network, Jun 15 (Box 4, Folder 78)
      - USS Providence, [fast attack submarine commissioning], Jul 27 (Box 4, Folder 79)
      - USS Pittsburgh, [fast attack submarine launching], Nov 23 (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - 1986
      - Good Friday, Mar 29 (Box 4, Folder 81)
      - USS Helena [fast attack submarine launching], Jun 28 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - 1987
      - "Disarm the Seas," May 29-31 (Box 4, Folder 83)
      - Twenty-fifth anniversary of the Cuban Missile Crisis/International Day of Disarmament, Oct 24-26 (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - 1988
      - USS Topeka [fast attack submarine launching], Jan 23 4 (Box 4, Folder 85)
      - USS San Juan [fast attack submarine commissioning], Sep 6 (Box 4, Folder 86)
      - USS Miami [fast attack submarine launching], Nov 12 (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - Plowshares
    - Actions
      - Trident Nein (1982 July 4), 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 88)
      - Plowshares #4 (1982 Nov 14), 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 89)
      - Avco Plowshares (1983 Jul 14) [Wilmington, Massachusetts] (Box 4, Folder 90)
      - Sperry Software Pair (1984 Aug 10) [Eagan, Minnesota] (Box 4, Folder 91)
      - Trident II Plowshares (1984 Oct 1) [Quonset Point, Rhode Island], 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 92)
      - Trident II Pruning Hooks (1985 Apr 18) [Quonset Point, Rhode Island] (Box 4, Folder 93)
      - Thames River Plowshares (1989 Sep 4) [New London, Connecticut] (Box 4, Folder 94)
    - Support groups
      - Plowshares Support Rhode Island, 1988, undated (Box 4, Folder 95)
      - Trident Nein/Plowshares #4 Support Committee, 1982-1984, undated (Box 4, Folder 96)
  - Trident system files
    - Electric Boat Shipyard [Groton, Connecticut]
      - "Alternative Use Study," 1984-1985 5 (Box 5, Folder 97)
      - Break-ins [re: security issues], 1982 (Box 5, Folder 98)
      - Contract negotiations with United States Navy [clippings], 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 99)
      - Cost over-runs for Trident construction, 1975-1982 (Box 5, Folder 100)